Guide to the Alfredo Castañeda Papers, 1935-1978
Department of Special Collections
Alfredo Castañeda Papers,
1935-1978
Special Collections M0353
Castañeda, Alfredo, 1923?-1981
8.5 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Provenance
Transferred from the University Archives, 1981.
Biographical Note
Alfredo Castaneda, a nationally prominent expert in multicultural education, was the first Mexican American to be appointed to a full professorship at Stanford University. He came to Stanford in 1972 from the University of California at Riverside, where he was professor of education and chairman of the Mexican American Studies Program. His publications include Mexican-Americans and Educational Change, 1971, and Cultural Democracy, Bicognitive Development and Education, 1974, written with Manuel Ramirez III. He served as consultant to the Western Interstate Commission for Higher Education, the U.S. Department of Health, Education and Welfare's National Center for Health Statistics, and HEW's Task Force on School Integration.
Scope and Content
This collection reflects Dr. Castaneda's work in multicultural and bilingual education, especially as it relates to Mexican American students. It includes elementary and secondary curriculum materials, grant applications for bilingual/bicultural education projects under Title VII legislation, materials from bilingual/multicultural programs in public schools, and secondary sources that he used in his university courses. Of particular note are student booklets and teacher's manuals produced by the Bay Area Bilingual Education League (BABEL), a consortium of Bay Area School Districts that provided comprehensive bilingual/bicultural programs to public schools. Some materials relate to Black Studies and bilingual education among ethnic groups other than Hispanic. Other papers in the collection include articles and books written by Dr. Castaneda and papers and dissertations of his students. The collection spans about twenty years, 1956-1978, with a few secondary sources from as early as 1935. The bulk of the collection falls between 1971 and 1978.
Container List
- SERIES I: WRITINGS OF ALFREDO CASTANEDA, 1956-1974
  - Assessmaent of Achievement Motivation in Mexican American Elementary School Children, 1974. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - The Children's Form of the Manifest Anxiety Scale, 1956. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Cultural Democracy, Bicognitive Development and Education, 1974.(with Manuel Ramirez) (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Mexican Americans and Educational Change, 1971. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Multi-Lingual Assessment Project Riverside Component, 1973. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Traditionalism, Modernism, and Ethnicity, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 6)
- SERIES II: STUDENT PAPERS AND DISSERTATIONS, 1975-1978
  - Arias, M. Beatriz, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Brown, Carl R.V., 1977 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Brown, Carl R.V., 1977 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Perez, Theresa R.L., 1978 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Rigby, Barbara E., n.d. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Young, Raquel B., 1976 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- SERIES III: BAY AREA BILINGUAL EDUCATION LEAGUE (BABEL), 1971-1976
  - Elementary Teachers' Materials, 1971-1973 (Box 3)
  - Elementary Teachers' Materials, 1971-1973 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Bilingual Alternatives for Secondary Teachers and Aides (BASTA), n.d. (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Teacher's Packet, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Non-Spanish Program Materials, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Student Materials, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous, 1971-1976 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- SERIES IV: MULTICULTURAL/BILINGUAL EDUCATION SOURCE MATERIALS, 1966-1976
  - Articles, bibilographies, brochures, pamphlets, and books arranged alphabetically by title; unbound items preceed bound items. (Box 6-9)
- SERIES V: CHICANO STUDIES INSTITUTE, 1970
  - Study materials prepared for the Summer 1970Institute, arranged alphabetically by title. (Box 9)
- SERIES VI: COURSE READINGS, 1935-1978
  - Adler, Peter S. Beyond Cultural Identity: Reflections on Cultural and Multicultural Man, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Ambron, Sueann, et.al. Effects of Day Care on Psychological Development in Young Children, research proposal, 1977. (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Ambron, Sueann, et.al. Supplement and Appendix to Research Proposal, 1977. (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Banks, James A. The Implications of Multicultural Education for Teacher Education, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Dong, Tim Tung Leung. Psychology of Asian-Americans, A Bibliography, 1975. (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Fitzgerald, Thomas K. Education and Identity: A Reconsideration of Some Models of Acculturation and Identity, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Gay, Geneva. Ethnic Identity in Early Adolescence: Some Implications for Instructional Reform, 1978. (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Gibson, Margaret Alison. Some Approaches to Multicultural Education in the United States: Some Concepts and Assumptions, 1975. (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Inkeles, Alex. Understanding and Misunderstanding Individual Modernity, 1976. (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Kamin, Leon J. Heredity, Intelligence, Politics, and Psychology, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Keogh, Barbara K. Perceptual and Cognitive Styles: Implications for Special Education, c. 1972. (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - McFee, Malcolm. The 150% Man, a Product of Blackfeet Acculturation, 1968. (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Office for Civil Rights. Memo: Elimination of Discrimination in the Assignment of Children to Special Education Classes for the Mentally Retarded. (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Ramirez, Manuel, III. Recognizing and Understanding Diversity: Multiculturalism and the Chicano Movement in Psychology, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Stonequist, Everett V. The Problem of the Marginal Man, 1935. (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Sue, Derald Wing. Dimensions of Cultural Identity: Implications for Counseling, 1977. (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - TenHouten, Warren D. Cognitive Sytles and the Social Order, 1971. (Box 10, Folder 17)
  - U.S. Department of HEW. Advance Data, 1978. (Box 10, Folder 18)
  - Valentine, Charles A. Deficit, Difference, and Bicultural Models of Afro-American Behavior, 1971. (Box 10, Folder 19)
  - Willie, Charles V. Marginality and Social Change, 1975. (Box 10, Folder 20)
  - Zaks, Vivian Calderon. A Measure of Ethnic Identity for Young Adult Mexican Americans, 1974. (Box 10, Folder 21)
  - Zavala, Celia. Role Models and Ethnic Identity Among Bilingual Teachers, 1978. (Box 10, Folder 22)
- SERIES VII: MULTICULTURAL/BILINGUAL PUBLIC SCHOOL PROGRAMS, 1971-1975
  - Pamphlets, booklets, bibliographies, proposals, handbooks, and curriculum materials from public schools in Alameda County, Los Angeles, Palo Alto, and San Jose. (Box 11)
- SERIES VIII: TITLE VII, ESEA, BILINGUAL/BICULTURAL PROGRAMS, 1972-1975
  - Guide to Title VII ESEA Bilingual Bicultural Projects in the United States, 1972-1973 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Proceedings; National Conference on Bilingual Education, April 14-15, 1972 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - U.S. Department of HEW, Bilingual Education Program. Criteria for Governing Grants Awards, 1976. (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - U.S. Department of HEW, Office of Education. A Process Evaluation of the Bilingual Education Program, 1973. (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Grant applications for Title VII Bilingual Programs in Bakersfield, Dos Palos, Fullerton, and Hollister, CA, 1975 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Grant applications for Title VII Bilingual Programs in Irvine, Montebello, Morgan Hill, Mountain View, and Northridge, CA, 1975 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Grant applications for Title VII Bilingual Programs in Norwalk, Sacramento, Salinas, and Thermal, CA, 1975 (Box 14, Folder 1)
- SERIES IX: STANFORD CENTER FOR RESEARCH AND DEVELOPMENT IN TEACHING, 1973-1975
  - Memoranda, Technical Reports, Occasional Papers, and other miscellaneous publications, 1973-1975. (Box 15-16)
- SERIES X: BLACK STUDIES, 1971-1975
  - Henderson, Donald M. Articles on Black Education, 1974-1975. (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Report on a One Day Workshop on the Delivery of Basic Skills to Black Students, 1972. (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Taylor, Orlando L. Articles on Black English, 1971-1973. (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Valentine, Charles. Deficit, Difference, and Bicultural Models of Afro-American Behavior, 1971. (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Atlanta Public Schools. Black Studies Bibliography, 1974. (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Atlanta Public Schools. Black Studies Curriculum Guide, 1974. (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - Favors, John and Kathryne. John Quincy Adams and the Amistad, 1974. (Box 17, Folder 7)
- SERIES IX: MISCELLANY, 1971-1974
  - Catalog of Curriculum Publications, Chicago Public Schools, 1974. (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Dialects and Interference with Learning to Read, n.d. (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Home Visiting with Mothers and Infants, 1971. (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - A Long Dark Hallway, 1971. (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Sex Differences, Sex Typing, and Women's Studies Bibiliography, n.d. (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Two handouts on ethnicity. (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - Whites for Rights, news release, n.d. (Box 18, Folder 7)